A Guide to the Mountain Lake: David Sherman Collection 1870-2002
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Mountain Lake: David Sherman Collection 1870-2002
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2004-014
0.5 cu. ft.; 1 manuscript box
The Mountain Lake: David Sherman Collection consists of papers collected by David Sherman of the U.S. Forest Service and Appalachian Trail Conference while working to establish a federal wilderness area around Mountain Lake in Giles County, Virginia during the 1980s. Materials include hotel brochures, magazine and guidebook articles, a dissertation about the lake, maps, federal reports about the environmental conditions, and research and correspondence about local land ownership.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Mountain Lake: David Sherman Collection was donated to the Special Collections by its collector in 2003.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mountain Lake is a 6,000 year old freshwater lake in Giles County, Virginia that is fed by cold underground springs. It was formerly known as Salt Pond, and the area sits atop Salt Pond Mountain along the eastern continental divide. A hotel or resort has operated at the privately owned site since 1857.
Around 1980, David Sherman of the U.S. Forest Service and the Appalachian Trail Conference became involved in the effort to designate the area around Mountain Lake as a federal wilderness area. Although unable to secure property including Mountain Lake itself, over eight thousand acres of Mountain Lake Wilderness area to the lake's north, including a portion of the Appalachian Trail, are now administered by the Jefferson National Forest.
Scope and Content
The Mountain Lake: David Sherman collection contains papers collected by David Sherman while he working to establish a federal wilderness area around Mountain Lake in Giles County, Virginia during the 1980s. Old hotel brochures and articles printed in local magazines and guidebooks dating from 1870 to 2002 provide historical background on the area. Maps and photographs provide geographic information about the land. There is also a copy of a doctoral dissertation on the history of Mountain Lake written by Frederick C. Marland, a Virginia Tech graduate. Other material in the collection documents Sherman's effort to preserve the Mountain Lake area. These items include federal studies and reports about the environmental conditions generated by federal agencies, copies of legislation, and research and correspondence about local land ownership.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by subject groupings. As the collection contains only twenty folders, no subdivisions into series were necessary.
Some collection material was originally stored in a three-ring binder marked "Mountain Lake, Virginia. Miscellaneous Documentation." The papers in the binder were removed, placed in folders corresponding to their tab-divided groupings and labeled (binder), then the folders were interfiled with other material according to subject.
Contents List
- Miscellaneous photographs, postcards, and maps of Mountain Lake region (binder) (Box-folder 1-1)
- Postcards sent to C. J. French in Crewe, VA and Narrows, VA showing Bedford County, Virginia sites, including Peaks of Otter, Flat Top, Apple Orchard Falls and Mountain Lake in Giles County, 1907-1912 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Photographs, Mountain Lake area by David Sherman, 1980 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Brochures, Mountain Lake Hotel (binder), n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Brochures, Mountain Lake and Giles County, VA, 1912-1984, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
- Photocopies of magazine and guidebook articles about Mountain Lake (binder), 1870-2002 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Publications containing articles about Mountain Lake, 1884-1974 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - The Gray Jacket (published monthly by the literary societies of the Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College), February 1884
  - Outdoors: Selected Verse and Prose with Illustrations from Photographs Taken at Mountain Lake, Virginia, edited by Edna Turpin, 1916
  - The Iron Worker, Spring 1947
  - Highlights in the Early History of Montgomery County, Virginia by Lula Porterfield Givens, 1966
  - Context: A Bulletin of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Spring 1974
- Correspondence about Mountain Lake, Frederick C. Marland to Goodridge Wilson, including typed transcript of a 1957 lecture by Dr. Ivey Forman Lewis, A History of Mountain Lake, (binder), 1965-1966 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Photocopy of 1967 Dissertation, The History of Mountain Lake, Giles County, Virginia: An Interpretation Based on Paleolimnology, by Frederick C. Marland (binder), 1980 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Report, Evaluation of Mountain Lake Scenic Area and Mountain Lake Biological Station, Giles County, Virginia for Registered Natural Landmark, by Dr. Ian A. Worley (binder), 1974 (Box-folder 1-10)
- Report, Cascades - Mountain Lake Recreation Composite, Blacksburg Ranger District, Jefferson National Forest, Virginia, prepared by Paul A. Timko (binder), 1977 (Box-folder 1-11)
- Report, Mountain Lake Wilderness Study Area: Final Environmental Impact Statement and Study Report, Jefferson National Forest, Virginia and West Virginia, ca. 1981 (Box-folder 1-12)
- Photocopies of correspondence and legislation, Mountain Lake Wilderness Study Area and Trails (binder), 1981-1984 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Report, A Proposal: Mountain Lake Wilderness, Jefferson National Forest, Virginia and West Virginia: Draft Environmental Impact Statement, 1981
  - Chapter photocopied from Hiking Virginia's National Forests by Karin Wuertz-Schaefer, 1977
- Deeds and plats from 1938-1977 showing property in the Mountain Lake area, compiled ca. 1980 (Box-folder 1-14)
- Maps (oversize) accompanying deeds to property in the Mountain Lake area, 1965-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 1-15)
- Deeds, Ownership Information and Map (binder), 1972-1980 (Box-folder 1-16)
- Mary Moody Northen biographical material, (binder), n.d. (Box-folder 1-17)
- Letter, Secretary of the U.S. Department of the Interior, C. D. Andrus to Mary Northen (binder), 1980 (Box-folder 1-18)
- Deeds and correspondence, Mary Northen property, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 1-19)
- Correspondence and newspaper clippings, Mountain Lake land use and ownership (binder), 1980-1988 (Box-folder 1-20)